In the previous lecture we looked at some of the key characteristics of A agents and we
said it has four key characteristics so planning, memory, tools, and action and remember
action is nothing but agents has some tools and when you execute those tools you take some
action.
Now let's go ahead and deep dive into each of these areas so we'll start with planning.
There are three ways in which an agent can do plan.
So the first one is chain of thought reasoning, then you have three of thought reasoning and
then finally you have the react reasoning and action.
Okay now let's go ahead and check how planning is done by agents.
So earlier we discussed that agents are powered by large language models or LMs and it's
the brain behind the agents.
Now the question that you might have in mind is how do agents actually do planning?
And if they're driven by large language model and let's say I sent a summarization task
to a large language model, it doesn't do any planning, it will just give me a response.
So how do agents driven by large language models actually do planning?
So there's a mechanism to it and let me just explain to you, let's say we have a user.
Now let's say user posts a simple question, 6 minus 4 plus 2 and it's been seen in research
that sometimes large language models are not able to solve even some of the simple mathematical
problems.
So the best way seen in research on how agent can solve this question is by breaking down
it into multiple steps and how you can make the agent do that is by providing few sample
outputs to help it learn on how to break down the problem.
So let's also call it as few short prompting.
So maybe what you will do is you will provide it another question and let's say 3 minus
2 plus 1 and then you show it the first step it needs to take is add these two so you
do 3 plus 1, then you say okay now you have the answer, then do minus 2 that's the second
step and the third step is you get the answer.
And then you pose this question that you have 6 minus 4 plus 2 which is the user question.
So when the user question plus this example of how to solve this problem is sent to
the agent driven by large language model what it will do for this user question is it will
break it into steps as it has been instructed in this sample output.
So first it will do 6 plus 2 as was shown here then the step 2 it's going to do the
subtraction and step 3 it's going to generate the answer and then you will see that it
has come up with the right outcome.
So basically for agents to do the planning you need to provide it the right prompt template
which will help it in breaking down a complex talks into multiple steps.
Now let's go ahead and take a look at various approaches to planning by AI agents.
So there are two, the first one is planning without feedback.
So if in planning without feedback we have two main approaches.
So we have chain of thought reasoning and I'm going to deep into this a lot more because
Amazon bedrock agents actually uses this then you also have three of thought reasoning.
Then the second approach is planning with feedback and again it has two approaches.
So we have react or reasoning plus action again Amazon bedrock uses this so I'm going
to deep down a little more into this and then we also have reflection.
Now let's take a look at chain of thought prompting what it means.
So chain of thought prompting enables complex reasoning capabilities for LLMs through intermediate
reasoning steps.
So as we had seen previously that once you provide an input to an agent driven by a large
language model and you provide it with some sample scenarios on how to solve the problems
and break it into steps and that's what then for new user request the agent would be able
to do.
So research shows that this is especially effective when you are trying to improve the capability
of the large language model for questions related to mathematics and common sense reasoning
as we had seen previously.
So you can read more about this research on through this link which I will provide as part
of this PDF.
So this example is part of the white vapor that I had just shown you the link too.
So what they did was as part of the standard prompting they given example to the model which
said okay Roger has five tennis balls he buys two more cans of tennis balls each can
has three tennis balls how many tennis balls does he have and then they said okay the
answer is 11 and now the question for agent the cafeteria had 23 apples if they use 20 to make
lunch and brought six more how many apples do they have.
So the model responded with the answer 27 which is incorrect.
Then they used chain of thought reasoning prop and here they gave the same question but
in the answer they showed it how to break down the problem into multiple steps and then
solve it.
So they said okay Roger started with five balls then two cans of three balls is six tennis
balls each then you add five and six and the answer is 11.
Here they just directly provided the answer then they gave it the same question that
was here and what the model did was it broke down the problem into multiple steps then
added here and it got the right answer and that's where the chain of thought reasoning
comes from where you provide the model with how to solve a problem through multiple steps
and then get the right answer okay that's chain of thought reasoning next we have three
of thought and that's this again planning without feedback so it's very similar to chain
of thought reasoning but the only thing different here is that when you provide an input
instead of generating one plan it will generate multiple approaches and then they will
vote and decide okay which is the best approach let's say they decided plan two is the
best approach then they will break down the plan two again into multiple steps and then
execute.
So the only difference between chain of thought and three of thought is that here there
will be multiple plans generated at each step and then you just select one so you can
see here it generates multiple thoughts per step creating a tree structure so I'm not
going to get into details of these because this is not what Amazon bedrock agents uses but
this is one of the possible approaches and this is again based on a white paper and you
can read a little bit more about this on why it is an effective prompting technique.
Now let's take a look at the second approach which is planning with feedback and the
most important one is reasoning and action also known as react and this word Amazon bedrock
agents uses and this is also the most popular framework for agent planning.
So you can see here react is an advanced prompting technique that combines reasoning and
action within a prompt so it is good for scenarios where external or internal data is required
to execute task and it also does dynamic execution where it can replan.
So remember when we are talking about hotel booking and LN booking the hotel is not available
then you go and replan the days.
So how does it work?
Now let's see the difference between chain of thought reasoning and react.
So in the case of chain of thought reasoning let's say you provide a user input to a large
language model it will break down into multiple subtas and then leave it there.
Then you can have the action where you execute those tasks but it will not be dynamic
execution.
So it will not be continuously replying so if it doesn't get a hotel booking it is not
going to replan.
Now in the case of react what happens is once the user input is sent to this agent driven
by a large language model it is going to break the task into multiple sub steps and then
execute them and once you get the output let's say you call and hotel.com API and you
got a booking ID then it's going to pass that observation and observation simply means
the output it is getting from some data source it is going to pass that observation to
the large language model and if it satisfies the user request great that is going to provide
that output to the user but if it does not then it's going to replan and re execute the
task again.
Now let's quickly try and understand this through an example let's say we have a user
request and which is from the previous few lectures so we have an AI agent and our John wants
to go on a skiing vacation so he sends this input to the agent and what the agent will
do is it will break down this user request into multiple tasks.
So let's say in the step one he checking the leave balance in the step two is going to
check the book a flight book a hotel so what it will do is once it has broken down it
into these three steps then it's going to execute the task maybe it will call the better
open knowledge basis and see if he has vacation days so the observe you'll get an observation
it says okay John has 20 vacation days so he will pass that feedback to the agent saying
that okay he has 20 vacation days then he will go and book a flight and he will make
an API call to the travel site and flight and see if the flight tickets are available
if they're available it's going to pass that feedback back to the large language model
then again it will execute the book hotel from the hotel site and let's say it says accommodation
not available and then it will send this feedback back to the large language model the
LLM will look at all the three feedbacks that he has received now it will know since
the hotel is not available it will do the replanting and then execute for a different
date after checking with the user so this is what React style of prompting does it's
more dynamic and combines the steps of breaking down the task and executing at the same
time okay that's pretty much it from this lecture I'll see in the next lecture thank you